Inventory to the Free to Choose video tape collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Free to Choose video tape collection
1977-1987
80201
Hoover Institution Archives
10 manuscript boxes, 10 motion picture film reels, 42 videoreels (26.6 linear feet)
Motion picture film, video tapes, and film strips of the television series Free to Choose, featuring Milton Friedman and relating to laissez-faire economics, produced in 1980 by Penn Communications and television station WQLN in Erie, Pennsylvania. Includes commercial and master film copies, unedited film, and correspondence, memoranda, and legal agreements dated from 1977 to 1987 relating to production of the series. Digitized copies of many of the sound and video recordings in this collection, as well as some of Friedman's writings, are available at http://miltonfriedman.hoover.org.
Friedman, Milton, 1912-2006
Penn Communications.
WQLN (Television station: Erie, Pa.)
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980, with increments received in 1988 and 1989.
Related Collection(s)
Milton Friedman papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Collected Works of Milton Friedman website, http://miltonfriedman.hoover.org
Collected Works of Milton Friedman Project records, Hoover Institution Archives
The Legacy of Milton and Rose Friedman's Free to Choose conference proceedings, 2003, Hoover Institution Archives
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Motion picture film, video tapes, and film strips of the television series Free to Choose, featuring Milton Friedman and relating to laissez-faire economics, produced in 1980 by Penn Communications and television station WQLN in Erie, Pennsylvania. Includes commercial and master film copies and unedited film, as well as project files, correspondence, memoranda, publicity materials, and legal agreements dated from 1977 to 1987 relating to production of the series.
Digitized copies of many of the sound and video recordings in this collection, as well as some of Friedman's writings, are available at http://miltonfriedman.hoover.org.
Economics.; Free enterprise.; Video tapes.; Motion pictures.
- Project Files, 1977-1981, 1987
  - Milton Friedman series, #1-10, draft outline of argument, 1977 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes correspondence.
  - Friedman proposal, proposal for a series of television programs, Public Broadcasting of Northwest Pennsylvania, Inc., 1977 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Bechtel Foundation, 1977-1980 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    Includes extensive correspondence with George Shultz.
  - FMC Foundation, correspondence, 1977-1980 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Firestone Tire and Rubber Company, correspondence, 1977-1980 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - General Motors Corporation, correspondence, 1977-1980 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - General Mills Foundation, correspondence, 1977-1980 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Getty Oil Company, 1977-1980 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - W. R. Grace and Company, correspondence, 1977-1980 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Working papers, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    Includes correspondence, Friedman project analysis, working schedule and responsibilities, budget, planning session, TV topics and key ideas, notes of the meetings, proposals and lecture list, and cash flow chart.
  - Invoices, expenses, 1980 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Friedman lecture series, 1978 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Friedman TV series and progress report, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Friedman underwriters, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Free to Choose, Chicago, remote, 1979 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Planning grants, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Participation, promotion for rebroadcasts of series, 1980 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Free to Choose, general information (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Videocassette/video disc - guide to the manuals, undated (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Milton Friedman series, winter, 1980 tune-in, media recommendations, 1979 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Friedman program description (titles and key ideas), 1978-1979 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Ohio state award, 1981 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Friedman dinners and luncheons, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Hallmark Cards, Inc., 1977-1980 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Solicitation, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Lilly Endowment, Inc., 1977-1981 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - John M. Olin Foundation, Inc., 1977-1980 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Pepsico, Inc., 1977-1980 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - L. E. Phillips Charities, Inc., 1977-1980 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Reader's Digest, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Sarah Scaife Foundation, Inc., 1977-1980 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Whittaker Corporation, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Legal opinions/Friedman materials, 1979 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - In-house, employees, and to watch file, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Friedman study guides, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Friedman, PBS, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Penn Communications, Inc., agreement, 1983 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Publicity, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Free to Choose broadcast dates, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Non-broadcast distribution, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Moynahan Landou Communications, public relations approach for WQLN-TV, 1978 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Milton Friedman script, 1987 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Friedman cassette sales, 1978-1981 (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - Friedman previewers, 1979 (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - Free to Choose, letters from other PBS stations, 1980 (Box-folder 3: 16)
  - Friedman contracts, video arts, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 3: 17)
  - NFIB (National Federation of Independent Business), 1979-1981 (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - Fundraising/thank you notes, 1981 (Box-folder 3: 19)
  - Denial of petitions for support with financial assistance, 1981 (Box-folder 3: 20)
- Correspondence, 1977-1981
  - A-D (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - E-H (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - I-L (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - M-P (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Q-T (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - U-Z (Box-folder 4: 6)
- Printed Matter, circa 1977-1981
  - Viewer's guide (Box-folder 4: 7)
    Guide to "ten stimulating television programs in which Milton Friedman, Nobel laureate, economist, and columnist, challenges us with startling facts and thought-provoking ideas, then responds to opposing views, raising brass-tack questions about the future of our free society."
  - Instructor's resource guide to Free to Choose, a television series by Milton Friedman (Box-folder 4: 8)
    Written by John M. Allen and David G. Armstrong, Center for Education and Research in Free Enterprise, A&M University, Texas.
  - Titles and key ideas (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Press releases: individual program descriptions (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Discussion leader's resource guide to Free to Choose, a television series by Milton Friedman, programs 1-10 (Box-folder 4: 11-12)
  - Personal statement of Milton Friedman on the series of ten films, programs 1-10 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - List of stations airing Free to Choose programs (Box-folder 5: 2)
    Includes repeat time.
  - Milton Friedman photographs (4 prints) (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Video guide orders (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Ten posters reflecting the theme of the programs (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Cartoons promoting free market (Box-folder 5; 6)
  - Order forms (Box-folder 5: 7)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1977-1985
  - Milton Friedman Speaks videorecordings, 1977-1978 (On-shelf shelf)
    Milton Friedman Speaks was a series of 15 lectures, with question and answer sessions, given by Friedman between 1977 and 1978 that formed the basis for the Free to Choose television series. Master copies, 27 two-inch videoreels.
    - "Who Protects the Consumer?," lecture 1, Pfizer Corporation, New York City, 1977 September 12
      - Reel 1 (Reel 10)
      - Reel 2, Q&A (Reel 11)
    - "Putting Learning Back in the Classroom," lecture 2, Harlem Parents for Vouchers, New York City, 1977 September 15
      - Reel 1 (Reel 14)
      - Reel 2, Q&A (Reel 15)
    - "Is Capitalism Humane?," lecture 3, Cornell University, 1977 September 27
      - Reel 1 (Reel 5)
      - Reel 2 (Reel 6)
      - Reel 3 (Reel 7)
    - "Who Protects the Worker?", lecture 4, WQLN-TV, Erie, Pennsylvania, 1977 September 29
      - Reel 1 (Reel 8)
      - Reel 2 (Reel 9)
    - "What Is America?," lecture 5, University of Chicago, 1977 October 3
      - Reel 1 (Reel 3)
      - Reel 2, Q&A (Reel 4)
    - "Myths That Conceal Reality," lecture 6, Utah State University, 1977 October 13
      - Reel 1 (Reel 18)
      - Reel 2 (Reel 19)
    - "Money and Inflation," lecture 7, University of San Diego/San Diego Chamber of Commerce, 1977 November 7
      - Reel 1 (Reel 23)
      - Reel 2 (Reel 24)
    - "Is Tax Reform Possible?," lecture 8, Americanism Education League, Pasadena, California, 1978 February 6
      - Reel 1 (Reel 21)
      - Reel 2, Q&A (Reel 22)
        Tape cut in two at 11:00 minutes.
    - "The Role of Government in a Free Society," lecture 9, Stanford University, 1978 February 9 (Reel 25)
    - "The Energy Crisis: A Humane Solution," lecture 10, Bank of America, San Francisco, California, 1978 February 10
      - Reel 1 (break in tape at 7:38 minutes) (Reel 1)
      - Reel 2, Q&A (Reel 2)
    - "What Is Wrong with the Welfare State," lecture 12, University of Rochester, 1978 February 23
      - Reel 1 (Reel 26)
      - Reel 2, Q&A (Reel 27)
    - "Free Trade: Producer vs. Consumer," lecture 13, Kansas State University, 1978 April 27
      - Reel 1 (Reel 16)
      - Reel 2, Q&A (Reel 17)
    - "Equality and Freedom in the Free Enterprise System," lecture 14, College of William and Mary, Newport News Campus, 1978 May 1
      - Reel 1 (Reel 12)
      - Reel 2, Q&A (Reel 13)
    - "The Economics of Medical Care," lecture 15, Mayo Foundation, Rochester, Minnesota, Q&A, 1978 May 19 (Reel 20)
  - Free to Choose (original series), 1980
    Each hour-long program consists of a segment of Milton Friedman discussing free market issues in various locations worldwide, followed by a discussion between Friedman and other scholars and experts.
    - Program 1 (#101), "The Power of the Market"
      - Transcript (Box-folder 6: 1)
      - VHS videocassette (Box 6)
      - 3/4-inch U-matic videocassette (Box 7)
      - 16mm motion picture film reel, 1200 ft. (On-shelf shelf)
      - One-inch videoreel (On-shelf shelf)
    - Program 2 (#102), "The Tyranny of Control"
      - Transcript (Box-folder 6: 2)
      - VHS videocassette (Box 6)
      - 3/4-inch U-matic videocassette (Box 7)
      - 16mm motion picture film reel, 1200 ft. (On-shelf shelf)
      - One-inch videoreel (On-shelf shelf)
    - Program 3 (#103), "Anatomy of Crisis"
      - Transcript (Box-folder 6: 3)
      - VHS videocassette (Box 6)
      - 3/4-inch U-matic videocassette (Box 7)
      - 16mm motion picture film reel, 1200 ft. (On-shelf shelf)
      - One-inch videoreel (On-shelf shelf)
        Label on videoreel indicates that it consists of two 30-minute shows.
    - Program 4 (#104), "From Cradle to Grave"
      - Transcript (Box-folder 6: 4)
      - VHS videocassette (Box 6)
      - 3/4-inch U-matic videocassette (Box 8)
      - 16mm motion picture film reel, 1200 ft. (On-shelf shelf)
      - One-inch videoreel (On-shelf shelf)
    - Program 5 (#105), "Created Equal"
      - Transcript (Box-folder 6: 5)
      - VHS videocassette (Box 6)
      - 3/4-inch U-matic videocassette (Box 8)
      - 16mm motion picture film reel, 1200 ft. (On-shelf shelf)
      - One-inch videoreel (On-shelf shelf)
    - Program 6 (#106), "What's Wrong with Our Schools?"
      - Transcript (Box-folder 6: 6)
      - VHS videocassette (Box 6)
      - 3/4-inch U-matic videocassette (Box 8)
      - 16mm motion picture film reel, 1200 ft. (On-shelf shelf)
      - One-inch videoreel (On-shelf shelf)
    - Program 7 (#107), "Who Protects the Consumer?"
      - Transcript (Box-folder 6: 7)
      - VHS videocassette (Box 7)
      - 3/4-inch U-matic videocassette (Box 8)
      - 16mm motion picture film reel, 1200 ft. (On-shelf shelf)
      - One-inch videoreel (On-shelf shelf)
    - Program 8 (#108), "Who Protects the Worker?"
      - Transcript (Box-folder 6: 8)
      - VHS videocassette (Box 7)
      - 3/4-inch U-matic videocassette (Box 8)
      - 16mm motion picture film reel, 1200 ft. (On-shelf shelf)
      - One-inch videoreel (On-shelf shelf)
        Label on videoreel indicates that it consists of one 30-minute show.
    - Program 9 (#109), "How to Cure Inflation"
      - Transcript (Box-folder 6: 9)
      - VHS videocassette (Box 7)
      - 3/4-inch U-matic videocassette (Box 8)
      - 16mm motion picture film reel, 1200 ft. (On-shelf shelf)
      - One-inch videoreel (On-shelf shelf)
    - Program 10 (#110), "How to Stay Free"
      - Transcript (Box-folder 6: 10)
      - VHS videocassette (Box 7)
      - 3/4-inch U-matic videocassette (Box 9)
      - 16mm motion picture film reel, 2000 ft. (On-shelf shelf)
      - One-inch videoreel (On-shelf shelf)
    - Sound discs (CDs) (Box 9)
      - Programs 1 and 2 (two copies)
      - Programs 3 and 4 (two copies)
      - Program 5
      - Programs 5 and 6
      - Programs 7 and 8
      - Programs 9 and 10
    - Teacher's guide
      Three units; each unit contains three sound cassettes and three sound and color film strips that furnish the basis for a wide variety of classroom projects.
      - Unit 1, The Line Between Freedom and Equality (Box 9)
        Includes "From Cradle to Grave," "Created Equal," and "How to Stay Free."
      - Unit 2, The Free Market and Business Cycles (Box 10)
        Includes "The Power of the Market," "Anatomy of Crisis," and "How to Cure Inflation."
      - Unit 3, Protection...or Freedom (Box 10)
        Includes "The Tyranny of Control," "Who Protects the Consumer?," and "Who Protects the Worker?"
  - Free to Choose: A Second Look videorecordings, 1985 (On-shelf shelf)
    Consists of the original series documentary segment, followed by a half-hour question and answer session with Milton Friedman and high school students. Edit master copies, 5 one-inch videoreels.
    - "The Power of the Market," 56:37
      Label: air master.
      Access
      Use copy reference number: 80201_v_0002334
    - "The Tyranny of Control," 58:54
    - "Anatomy of Crisis," 58:15
    - "Created Equal," 57:40
    - "How to Cure Inflation," 58:12